Guide to the Margaret "Peg" Johnston Papers, 1989-2018 and undated RL.00639
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
Margaret "Peg" Johnston papers
1965-2018 and undated
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
Johnston, Peg, (Margaret R.)
RL.00639
7.5 Linear Feet
Abortion rights activist. Director, Southern Tier Women's Services in upstate New York. Former President of the Abortion Conversation Project; founder and past president of the National Coalition of Abortion Providers. Collection comprises primarily printed materials that document Johnston's work as an activist at the national level. Includes the abortion provider newsletter Feminist Caucus News (1989-1991), which later became Networks (1992-1998 and undated). In addition, there are copies of Johnston's counseling aids, including the workbooks Abortion: Which Method is Right for Me?; Pregnant? Need Help? Pregnancy Options Workbook; and A Guide to Emotional and Spiritual Resolution After an Abortion. There are order forms, advertising, and occasional publications associated with the workbooks and other items offered for sale; an article pro-choice political activism for the 1996 elections; a few letters, notes, and memos by Johnston, including two undated pages with her notes on the material's historical significance. Also includes a copy of Morgen Goodroe's Abortion Resolution Workbook, greeting cards, Religious Groups for Choice ephemera, and other abortion counseling information.
Access Restrictions
Some materials will need additional screening before use.
Provenance
Gift, 2010-2014
Biographical Note
Abortion rights activist. Director, Southern Tier Women's Services in upstate New York. Former President of the Abortion Conversation Project; founder and past president of the National Coalition of Abortion Providers.
Collection Overview
Collection comprises primarily printed materials that document Johnston's work as an activist at the national level. Includes the abortion provider newsletter Feminist Caucus News (1989-1991), which later became Networks (1992-1998 and undated). In addition, there are copies of Johnston's counseling aids, including the workbooks Abortion: Which Method is Right for Me?; Pregnant? Need Help? Pregnancy Options Workbook; and A Guide to Emotional and Spiritual Resolution After an Abortion. There are order forms, advertising, and occasional publications associated with the workbooks and other items offered for sale; an article pro-choice political activism for the 1996 elections; a few letters, notes, and memos by Johnston, including two undated pages with her notes on the material's historical significance. Also includes a copy of Morgen Goodroe's Abortion Resolution Workbook, greeting cards, Religious Groups for Choice ephemera, and other abortion counseling information.
Conditions Governing Access
Contents of Box 3 closed to use
Abortion counseling -- United States; Abortion counseling -- United States -- Periodicals; Pro-choice movement -- United States; Pro-choice movement -- United States -- Periodicals; Abortion services -- United States -- Periodicals; Abortion services -- United States; Johnston, Peg, (Margaret R.); Sallie Bingham Center for Women's History and Culture; National Abortion Federation (U.S.) -- Periodicals
- Margaret "Peg" Johnston Papers, 1989-2008, 2 boxes
  Scope and Contents note
  Collection comprises primarily printed materials that document Johnston's work as an activist at the national level. Includes the abortion provider newsletter Feminist Caucus News (1989-1991), which later became Networks (1992-1998 and undated). In addition, there are copies of Johnston's counseling aids, including the workbooks Abortion: Which Method is Right for Me?; Pregnant? Need Help? Pregnancy Options Workbook; and A Guide to Emotional and Spiritual Resolution After an Abortion. There are order forms, advertising, and occasional publications associated with the workbooks and other items offered for sale; an article pro-choice political activism for the 1996 elections; a few letters, notes, and memos by Johnston, including two undated pages with her notes on the material's historical significance. Also includes a copy of Morgen Goodroe's Abortion Resolution Workbook, greeting cards, Religious Groups for Choice ephemera, and other abortion counseling information.
  - Printed materials, arranged chronologically, 1989-2008 (Box 1)
  - Abortion counseling information and publications (Box 2)
  - Connecting the Head and Heart: Abortion Counseling (includes VHS tape) (Box 2)
  - Ephemera: Religious Groups for Choice (Box 2)
  - Greeting cards (Box 2)
  - National Abortion Federation (NAF) Feminist Caucus materials (Box 2)
  - Newsletter Materials: FLASHpoint (Box 2)
  - Newsletter: FLASHpoint, introductory issue and Vol. 1, no. 1 (Box 2)
  - November Gang/Early NAF Feminist Caucus Material (Box 2)
  - Pregnant? Need Help? Workbook Material (Box 2)
  - Trends in Women's Healthcare Advisory Board meeting, 2007 (Box 2)
- Accession (2014-0144) 1965-2005
  Scope and Contents
  Addition consists of research and teaching material as well as about 30 items produced by the National Abortion Federation including conference syllabi, reports, newsletters, and resource materials for providers.
  - NAF: Field Guide to Anti-Abortion Extremists, 1992 (Box 3)
  - NAF: Field Guide to Anti-Abortion Extremists, 2004 (Box 3)
  - NAF: Anti-Abortion Extremists, Profiles (Box 3)
  - NAF: 20 Years of Courage (Annual Meeting Syllabus), 1996 (Box 3)
  - NAF: 30 Years of Legal Abortion (Annual Meeting Syllabus), April 5-8, 2003 (Box 3)
  - NAF: Abortion & Breast Cancer Response Kit, 2002 (Box 3)
  - NAF: Abortion Care for the 21st Century, 1999 (Box 3)
  - NAF: Abortion: Unity in Diversity (Annual Meeting Workbook), 1994 (Box 3)
  - NAF: Annual Meeting Program and Syllabi, 1997; 1998; 2002 (Box 3)
  - NAF: Clinic Violence Material, 1977-2003 (Box 3)
  - NAF: Coming Together: Science, Politics & Ethics (Annual Meeting Syllabus), April 16-19, 2005 (Box 3)
  - NAF Counseling Workshop (Annual Meeting Workshop), April 15-19, 2000 (Box 3)
  - NAF: The Facts about Butyric Acic, 1999 (Box 3)
  - NAF: Guides to Abortion Providers, 1988-1996 (Box 3)
  - NAF: Medicine in the Millenium (Annual Meeting Syllabus), April 15-19, 2000 (Box 3)
  - NAF: Navigating the Barriers (Annual Meeting Syllabus), April 17-20, 2004 (Box 3)
  - NAF: Pain Management Reducing Patient Discomfort and Providing Anxiety, September 18-19, 1994 (Box 3)
  - NAF: The Role of Physical Assistants, Nurse Practitioners and Nurse Midwives in Providing Abortions, 1996 (Box 3)
  - National Abortion Federation Papers, 1997-1999 (Box 3)
  - NAF: Post-Grad Seminar, 1996 (Box 3)
  - NAF: Quarterly (Newsletter), 1980-1982 (Box 3)
  - NAF: STANDARDS, 1980 (Box 3)
  - Achieving Access and Reproductive Equity Grassroots Organizing Manual, 2000 (Box 3)
  - Articles about abortion and family planning, 1978-1997 (Box 3)
  - Feminist Majority Foundation: Clinic Violence Material, 1995-1999 (Box 3)
  - Homework Questions from "Connecting the Head and Heart: Abortion Counseling", 1992 (Box 3)
  - The New York Record: The Impact of Universally Available Birth Control (Planned Parenthood of New York City), 1965-1970 (Box 3)
  - Our Daughter's Decisions (Allan Guttmacher Institute), 1992 (Box 3)
  - Rx for Safety: Women's Healthcare Clinic Security Guide (Feminist Majority Foundation), 1995 (Box 3)
- Accession 2018-0141, 1
  - Abortion Care Network Papers, 2009 (Box 4)
    Conditions Governing Access
    Includes financial information. Needs additional screening before use.
  - Abortion Care Network, 2012-2014, 2016, 2018 (Box 4)
  - Abortion Conservation Project Board Meting Notes, 2006-2007 (Box 4)
  - Abortion Conservation Project, undated (Box 4)
  - ACP's for RCRC, 2002-2004 (Box 4)
  - Teen Parent, 2003, 2005-2006 (Box 4)
  - National Coalition of Abortion Providers History, 1990-1991 (Box 4)
  - NCAP Board Papers, 1990-2007; 4 folders (Box 4)
  - NCAP re: potab, 2002-2004 (Box 4)
    ACP, Charlotte Taft (written on folder)
  - Letter from Taft to Johnston, 1990-2005, 2017 (Box 4)
  - Faith Aloud, 2010-2016 (Box 4)
  - Early Southern Tier Women's Services, 1981-1984 (Box 4)
  - Southern Tier Women's Services Clinic Papers, 1986-2004 (Box 4)
  - Margaret Johnston papers; Trials..., 1987-1991 (Box 4)
    Includes financial and legal information. Needs additional screening before use.
  - Margaret Johnston papers; Responses to Anti's National, 1984-1985, 1994 (Box 4)
  - Anti-abortion lit letters; Southern Tier Women's Services, 1996-1998, 2000-2007 (Box 4)
  - Southern Tier Women's Services, 1981-1986, 1990-1994 (Box 4)
    1) Pt surveys on anti harassment 2) letters from anti's 3) community response (written on folder)
  - Southern Tier Women's Services letters to clinic (Anti's mostly), 1981-1986, 1996-1998, 2003 (Box 4)
    Includes legal information. Needs additional screening before use.
  - miscellaneous papers National early research and best practices etc., 1969-1986, 1991-1994 (Box 4)
  - National news miscellaneous, 1983-1988, 1993-1995 (Box 4)
  - letter from Parkinson to Johnston, 2016 (Oversize-folder 1)
  - feminist clinics; Margaret Johnston papers, 1983-1987 (Box 4)
  - unfoldered materials, 1989-2001, 2006-2014 (Box 4)
  - Anti-abortion lit, 1989-1997, 2010-2013 (Box 5)
  - Bridging Care & Justice, 2006 (Box 5)
    1 binder
  - Video - translation project, 1993-1994, 2008 (Box 5)
  - Counseling video; Head and Heart video & early dicussion, 1991-1992 (Box 5)
  - Southern Tier Women's Services, Johnston papers, counseling training (early), 1978-1982, 1992, 1997 (Box 5)
  - National Abortion Federation via Peg Johnston, notes on workshops, handouts, etc. especially abortion counseling, 1992-2004 (Box 5)
  - newspaper clipping: Maryland abortion clinic bombed, 1984 (Box 5)
  - Exhale, 2002-2004 (Box 5)
  - Peg Johnston, 1979, 1995; 2 items (Box 5)
    2 books
  - Pro-choice booklets, 1990-2003; 12 items (Box 5)
  - early Abortion Care Network, transition newsletter, 2008-2009, 2012 (Box 5)
  - Pro-chouce report, late (80% majority), 1994-1999 (Box 5)
  - National Coalition of Abortion letters, 2001-2008 (Box 5)
  - National Coalition of Abortion letters, 1996-2000 (Box 5)
  - miscellaneous pro-choice publications, 1992-1998, 2000-2007 (Box 5)
  - early medical ab France, 1986-1992; 2 folders (Box 5)
  - National Abortion Federation newletters & alerts (mostly security), 1989-2000 (Box 5)
  - Margaret Johnston papers, Johnston & Tepe, undated (Box 5)
  - National Abortion Federation 25th Anniversary Video, undated (Box 6, Video-cassette RL00639-VHS-0001)
  - National Coalition of Abortion Providers: Promoting a National Conversation on Abortion, undated (Box 6, Video-cassette RL00639-VHS-0002)
  - Charlotte Taft - Chicago, undated (Box 6, Video-cassette RL00639-VHS-0003)
  - A Matter of Propaganda; A Matter of Choice, undated (Box 6, Video-cassette RL00639-VHS-0004)
  - "Higher Laws" Biblical, Historical, and Present Day Perspective on Civil Disobedience (Box 6, Video-cassette RL00639-VHS-0005)
  - Abotion In Translation: Spanish, 1994 (Box 6, Video-cassette RL00639-VHS-0006)
  - Connecting the Head & the Heart: Abortion Counseling A Discussion for Providers & Pro-Choice Audiences, 1992 (Box 6, Video-cassette RL00639-VHS-0007)
  - Nov. Gang Abduction, 1991 February 11 (Box 6, Video-cassette RL00639-VHS-0008)
  - From Danger to Dignity: The Fight for Safe Abortions, 1995 (Box 6, Video-cassette RL00639-VHS-0009)
  - The Massacre of Innocence, 1988 (Box 6, Video-cassette RL00639-VHS-0010)
  - Abortion: Desperate Choices, undated (Box 6, Video-cassette RL00639-VHS-0011)
  - Freedom, undated (Box 6, Video-cassette RL00639-VHS-0012)
  - We Can Do Better: Inside an Independent Abortion Clinic, 2002 (Box 6, Video-cassette RL00639-VHS-0013)
  - Natural - Simple - Safe, Philosophies and Techniques of late term abortion services at Womens Health Care Services (Box 6, Video-cassette RL00639-VHS-0014)
  - 147 Front Street Invasion, 1989 January 11, 1989 July 25-26 (Box 6, Video-cassette RL00639-VHS-0015)
  - NCAP-Opening the Conversation about Abortion: A Congressional Briefing on the Abortion Experience, 03/05/2001 (Box 6, Video-cassette RL00639-VHS-0016)
  - Excerpts from NCAP Congressional Briefing on Capital Hill, Washington D.C., 2001 March 05 (Box 6, Video-cassette RL00639-VHS-0017)
  - Blockade At Buffalo GYN Womenservices, 1992 October 28 (Box 6, Video-cassette RL00639-VHS-0018)
  - Pro-Choice, Inc. Ad Campaign (Box 6, Video-cassette RL00639-VHS-0019)
  - HBO Army of God, 2001 April 01 (Box 6, Video-cassette RL00639-VHS-0020)
  - Rescue Training I, undated (Box 6, Video-cassette RL00639-VHS-0021)
  - Rescue Training II, undated (Box 6, Video-cassette RL00639-VHS-0022)
  - Rescue Training III, undated (Box 6, Video-cassette RL00639-VHS-0023)
  - Abortion: Hard Truth / Hard Truth "Seeing Is Believing", undated (Box 6, Video-cassette RL00639-VHS-0024)
  - Operation Rescue; Blockade at Bflo. GYN Women's Services, 1989 (Box 6, Video-cassette RL00639-Umatic-0001)
  - Abstinence comes to Albuguerque, 2005 (Box 6, Video-disc RL00639-DVD-0001)
  - Sacred Choices and Abortion: 10 New Things to Talk About, 2004 (Box 6, Video-disc RL00639-DVD-0002)
  - Faith Aloud: National Launch, 2010 (Box 7, Video-disc RL00639-DVD-0003)
    Originally from Box 4 Folder Faith Aloud
  - Faith Aloud: Words of Comfort: Clergy Women Speak about Abortion, 2010 (Box 7, Video-disc RL00639-DVD-0004)
  - Range of Emotional Recovery / The Healing Process - Pam O'Leary; 1997 Risk Management Seminar; National Abortion Federation; Resourceful Recordings; 6-9720 (Box 6, Audio-cassette RL00639-CS-0017)
  - Emotional Care of Women Terminating Due to Fetal Indication - George R. Tiller, MD; 1997 Risk Management Seminar; National Abortion Federation; Resourceful Recordings; 17-9720 (good!) (STWS Peg Johnston) (Box 6, Audio-cassette RL00639-CS-0018)
  - The Healing Choice: A Guide to Normal Emotional Recovery After an Abotion & Panel Discussion - Candace DuPuy, PhD & Dana Dovitch, PhD; 1997 Risk Management Seminar; National Abortion Federation; Resourceful Recordings; 19-9720 (Box 6, Audio-cassette RL00639-CS-0019)
  - Range of Emotional Recovery / The Healing Process - Dennis Christensen, MD; 1997 Risk Management Seminar; National Abortion Federation; Resourceful Recordings; 7-9720 (STWS Pg.) (Box 6, Audio-cassette RL00639-CS-0020)
  - Emotional Aftercare of Women with Underlying Serious Psychological Issues - Laura Bierut, MD; 1997 Risk Management Seminar; National Abortion Federation; Resourceful Recordings; 18-9720 (Box 6, Audio-cassette RL00639-CS-0021)
  - Counseling Guidelines: Three Approaches to Compliance - A. Wilson; A. Baker; J. Feldman; M. Rawling; 1996 Risk Management Seminar; National Abortion Federation; Resource Recordings; 5-9617 (Box 6, Audio-cassette RL00639-CS-0022)
  - How We Value Our Services ~ - Susan Landau & Laura Small; 21TH Annual Meeting; National Abortion Federation; Resourceful Recordings; 20-9708, 1997 (Box 6, Audio-cassette RL00639-CS-0011)
  - Short Topics in Administration - Peg Johnston; Ashley Phillips; T Sobieski-Joy; Deboarah VanDerhei; Beverly Whipple; 21TH Annual Meeting; National Abortion Federation; Resourceful Recordings; 9-9708, 1997 (Box 6, Audio-cassette RL00639-CS-0012)
  - Post Graduate Seminar: Early Abortion - Panel Discussion 21TH Annual Meeting; National Abotion Federaion; Resourceful Recordings; 1E - 9708 Part 5 (Admin's Issues), 1997 (Box 6, Audio-cassette RL00639-CS-0013)
  - Short Topics in Administration ~ ~ Administrative Track; A World Vision of Choice; Resourceful Recordings; Tape # 16-9809 (Good! CPT. Diversity Francine Thompson), 1998 (Box 6, Audio-cassette RL00639-CS-0014)
  - 18-9415 Tools to Assist Clients with Emotional Issues; part 2; Fall Risk Management Seminar; Resourceful Recordings; (Southern Women) (4), undated (Box 6, Audio-cassette RL00639-CS-0015)
  - Creating Excellence - Deni-Thurman-Eyer; Nancy Mosher; Jeri Rasmussen; 21TH Annual Meeting; National Abortion Federation; Resourceful Recordings; 21-9708, 1997 (Box 6, Audio-cassette RL00639-CS-0016)
  - When the Battle Raged; SIDE ONE: Ready to Fly / Close To Your Heart / I'm Crying For You Baby / When the Battle Raged; SIDE TWO: If You Believe Abortion Is Murder, Act Like It's Murder, 1986 (Box 7, Audio-cassette RL00639-CS-0023)
  - Recognizing and Responding to the Diverse Spiritual Concerns of our Clients; Counseling Track; Tape # 18-9809, 1998 (Box 7, Audio-cassette RL00639-CS-0024)
  - "Breaking the Abortion Deadlock" - Nicki Nichols Gamble; Eileen McDonagh, PhD; Janet Benshoof, Esq; 18-9708, 1997 (Box 7, Audio-cassette RL00639-CS-0025)
  - Legal / Legislative Update' Legal / Political Track; Tape # 24-9809, 1998 (Box 7, Audio-cassette RL00639-CS-0026)
  - Providing Medical Abortion Services Part 4; Faculty; PC2d, 1999 (Box 7, Audio-cassette RL00639-CS-0027)
  - Clendennin NY Times; Henshaw - Clinic Harassment, 1986 (Box 7, Audio-cassette RL00639-CS-0028)
  - 93AWP-12 Connecting the Head and Heart: New Ideas in Abortion Counseling: Peg Johnston, Pam O'Leary; AWP * 18th Annual Conference * Re-Membering Our Wholeness, undated (Box 7, Audio-cassette RL00639-CS-0029)
  - Prayer for AB pt "Rhonda", undated (Box 7, Audio-cassette RL00639-CS-0030)
  - 18-9415 Tools to Assist Clients with Emotional Issues - Charlotte Taft; Wrap Up and Evaluation - Norma Aresti, undated (Box 7, Audio-cassette RL00639-CS-0031)
  - Remembering Iphigenia: Voice, Resonance, and a Talking Cure, 1996 April 26-27 (Box 7, Audio-cassette RL00639-CS-0032)
  - 99NAF-6 Adolescent Sexuality: Current Development Theory, 1999 (Box 7, Audio-cassette RL00639-CS-0033)
  - 99NAF-22 Negotiating Strategies for Clinic Directors, 1999 (Box 7, Audio-cassette RL00639-CS-0034)
  - 99NAF-7 Staff Diversity: How Much Is Enough?, 1999 (Box 7, Audio-cassette RL00639-CS-0035)
  - 99NAF-16 Plenary Session: Reproductive Rights are Human Rights, 1999 (Box 7, Audio-cassette RL00639-CS-0036)
  - 99NAF-20 Deconstructing Counselors' Attitudes Towards Abortion, 1999 (Box 7, Audio-cassette RL00639-CS-0037)
  - 99NAF-25 Keynote Address, 1999 (Box 7, Audio-cassette RL00639-CS-0038)
  - Obscene/threatening phone calls; Obscene Call (Rafael Martinez?), 1988 Spring (Box 7, Audio-cassette RL00639-CS-0039)
  - Obscene/threatening calls (Martinez?); Obscene Calls (Rafael Martinez?), 1988 Spring (Box 7, Audio-cassette RL00639-CS-0040)
  - Post Graduate Seminar: Early Abortion - Panel Discussion; 21TH Annual Meeting; National Abotion Federaion; Resourceful Recordings; 1C - 9708 Part 3 (STWS Peg Johnston) (PtB goud), 1997 (Box 7, Audio-cassette RL00639-CS-0001)
  - 9-9415 A Holistic Approach to Pain Management - Amy McGrane The Physicians Perspective - Moly Rawling MD; Fall Risk Management Seminar; Resourceful Recordings (STWS Peg Johnston), 1997 (Box 7, Audio-cassette RL00639-CS-0002)
  - Post Graduate Seminar: Early Abortion - Panel Discussion 21TH Annual Meeting; National Abotion Federaion; Resourceful Recordings; 1D - 9708 Part 4 (STWS Peg Johnston) (RN & M... Paul), 1997 (Box 7, Audio-cassette RL00639-CS-0003)
  - 17-9415 Indentifying Red Flags that Predict Poor Coping - Anne Baker, MA; Fall Risk Management Seminar Resourceful Recordings (So. Tier Women's Services) (2), undated (Box 7, Audio-cassette RL00639-CS-0004)
  - Medications in Abortion Practice: A Pharmological Review ~ Medical Track; A World Vision of Choice; Resourceful Recordings; Tape # 12-9809 (STWS Peg Johnston), 1998 (Box 7, Audio-cassette RL00639-CS-0005)
  - The Theory and Practice of Healthy Risk Re-direction ~ Counseling Tack; A World Vision of Choice; Resourceful Recodings; Tape #17-9809 (STWS Johnston), 1998 (Box 7, Audio-cassette RL00639-CS-0006)
  - Post Graduate Seminar: Early Abortion - Panel Discussion; 21TH Annual Meeting; National Abortion Federation; Resourceful Recordings; 1B-9708 Part 2 (STWS Peg Johnston) (50-50), 1997 (Box 7, Audio-cassette RL00639-CS-0007)
  - 99NAF-21 Medical Conditions: Impact on Abortion Decision-Making: Dr.'s B. Ferguson, E. Wiebe, G. Tiller; NAF's 23rd Annual Meeting *Atlanta*; Recorded Live by: Professional Programs, Inc.; Side 1 of 2 (STWS Peg Johnston), 1999 (Box 7, Audio-cassette RL00639-CS-0008)
  - 99NAF-18 Responding to Lower Patient Loads; Ruth Arick, Peg Johnston; NAF's 23rd Annual Meeting *Atlanta*; Recorded Live by: Professional Programs, Inc.; Side 1 of 2, 1999 (Box 7, Audio-cassette RL00639-CS-0009)
  - Post Graduate Seminar: Early Abortion - Panel Discussion; 21TH Annual Meeting; National Abortion Federation; Resourceful Recordings; 1A-9708 Part 1 (STWS Peg Johnston) (50-50), 1997 (Box 7, Audio-cassette RL00639-CS-0010)